<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">DC:TITLE</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">The Seasonal Differences of North and South Slopes in Controlling the Activities of the Columbian Ground Squirrel</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/Users/mlcenzer/Documents/History%20of%20ecology%20readings/Shaw%201925.pdf</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.OriginalURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/Users/mlcenzer/Documents/History%20of%20ecology%20readings/Shaw%201925.pdf</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">application/pdf</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">TIKA_DC:TITLE</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">The Seasonal Differences of North and South Slopes in Controlling the Activities of the Columbian Ground Squirrel</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes>The Seasonal Differences of North and South Slopes in Controlling the Activities of the Columbian Ground Squirrel
 
 The Seasonal Differences of North and South Slopes in Controlling the Activities of theColumbian Ground SquirrelAuthor(s): William T. ShawSource: Ecology, Vol. 6, No. 2 (Apr., 1925), pp. 157-162Published by: Wiley on behalf of the Ecological Society of AmericaStable URL: https://www.jstor.org/stable/1929371Accessed: 17-06-2021 16:24 UTC
 JSTOR is a not-for-profit service that helps scholars, researchers, and students discover, use, and build upon a wide
range of content in a trusted digital archive. We use information technology and tools to increase productivity and
facilitate new forms of scholarship. For more information about JSTOR, please contact support@jstor.org.
 
Your use of the JSTOR archive indicates your acceptance of the Terms &amp; Conditions of Use, available at
https://about.jstor.org/terms
Ecological Society of America, Wiley are collaborating with JSTOR to digitize, preserve andextend access to Ecology
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
 THE SEASONAL DIFFERENCES OF NORTH AND SOUTH
 SLOPES IN CONTROLLING THE ACTIVITIES OF
 THE COLUMBIAN GROUND SQUIRREL
 WILLIAM T. SHAW
 Agricultural Experiment Station, State College of Washington 1
 The territory surrounding Pullman, Washington, is a part of the region known as the Palouse country, which is itself a part of an extensive stratified
 lava plateau. This plateau has weathered into a collection of dome-shaped
 hills, without any great regularity of placement; hence, the variation in ac- tivities of life. These hills, however, have one thing in common, and that
 d~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~ia UM
 FIG. I. Palouse Country, Pullman, Washington. The foreground represents a south- west slope, the left-middle distance a north slope, and the right-middle distance a north- east slope. In the immediate foreground is seen a den of the Columbian ground squirrel.
 is a gradual slope to the southwest, and a rather abrupt drop down the north- east side (Fig. i). Geologists consider this formation to be due in part to the action of the prevailing winds which have blown from the southwest and
 1 Published with the approval of the Director of the Washington Agricultural Ex- periment Station as Scientific Paper No. i i8, College of Agriculture and Experiment Station, Pullman, Washington.
 I57
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
 i58 WILLIAM T. SHAW Ecology, Vol. VI, No. 2
 west, carrying with them dust clouds of disintegrated lava. This dust is driven gently or with force, depending upon the velocity of the wind, up the long southwest slope until it reaches the summit of the hill, when it settles slowly on the quiet side, there to produce a sharp downward slope in notice- able contrast to the opposite side. To believe that this action is still in
 progress we have but to notice the earth-blackened snow banks of the north-
 east hill slopes in spring.
 In like manner the snow is piled deeply on these northeast slopes. Here, from year to year the winter storms heavily drift the banks of snow, which escape the rays of the spring sun during the greater part of the day. There- fore, long after the southwest slopes have been uncovered by the combined action of sun, wind and rain we still see the white banks of the northeast aspects. Standing on any elevation in this neighborhood, during the month of April for instance and looking southwest, one sees long horizontal lines of snow still piled against the northern hillside; directing the vision to the north-
 east no snow is visible, nothing but bare southwest sloping fields drying in the spring wind and sun. Between them lies what is known locally as a draw (Fig. I). Through these hollows or diminutive valleys sometimes passes a
 stream, of more or less seasonal duration. Nor are these hills of great height at Pullman. In the bottom of the draw the elevation is 2,340 feet. On the
 Campus of the State College, well towards the top of a south and west sloping hill, the bench-mark reads 2,536 feet, or a difference of almost 200 feet in rise in less than half a mile.
 This condition of slight elevation, and more especially the northeast and southwest slope, together with the sun exposure, produces a variation in the development of plant and animal life of about ten days. Accordingly, we find the Columbian ground squirrel Citellus columbianus distinctly and de- cidedly influenced. He comes from hibernation earlier, breeds earlier, and returns again to aestivation sooner on the southwest than on the northeast side of the hill. Just how sharp a line exists between these two local condi- tions is a subject which would bear considerable further investigation. The following observations, however, indicate the existence of these local differ- ences.
 <Node id="4996"/>During the six seasons of investigation, notes were taken with special ref- erence to four points, namely: <Node id="5103"/>the difference in the time<Node id="5129"/> of coming from hibernation, the effect upon the rutting, the influence upon the time of ap- pearance of the young from their brood nests, and the time for returning to aestivation.<Node id="5310"/>
 In i9ii the first squirrels were observed out of hibernation in a warm southwest exposure, well down in the draw, on the 8th of March. They were first observed rutting on March 13, and the first young were observed coming from the burrows on the south slopes on May 9. These dates are approxi-
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
 April, I925 SEASONAL DIFFERENCES 159
 mately the same as the average for other seasons. The snow fall was mod-
 erate during the months of January, February and March, there having fallen
 32.75 inches. In the months of January, February and March, I912, the total snow fall
 was 20.25 inches. This, however, stayed on the ground until well into March,
 e.g., on March 3 the ground was still covered with snow on the south slope,
 and the <Node id="6171"/>mean temperature was I8 degrees F<Node id="6204"/>.
 A_
 FIG. 2. Vertical section of a snowbank through which a squirrel was forced to dig, tunneling over two feet of snow to free himself from a hibernation den buried by a
 northeast slope snowdrift, 1917 The exposed surface of the snowdrift, at B. is covered with a substantial deposit of soil carried there by southwest winter winds. The ground
 exit of the squirrel is at A, the snow exit at B.
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
 i6o WILLIAM T. SHAW Ecology, Vol. VI, No. 2
 <Node id="6774"/>On March I the snow was largely gone from the southwest slopes, while plenty remained on the northeast sides of the hills. On this date squirrels
 were <Node id="6926"/>first seen from hibernation<Node id="6953"/>, and on the 9th many were out on the south- west slopes. Yet none were observed rutting; probably most of those noticed
 out were males. Not until ten days later, March I I, were squirrels seen on
 the northeast slope, where there was still plenty of snow. On March I3 a
 solitary squirrel was observed on a wide snow field, on a northeast slope, sit-
 ting motionless at the entrance of his hibernation exit for over half an hour.<Node id="7385"/>
 He had dug through several inches of snow and sat there, suggesting the old superstition of the wood chuck and his shadow. On this same date, less than two hundred yards away, on the southwest slope of the same draw, while this
 northlander was taking the first view of the outer world other squirrels were
 rutting, chasing about among the blossoming buttercups, in full view of the
 opposite snowfields.
 One could imagine the case of a Chinook or a warm rain taking all of the
 snow off evenly, in which case the activities would still be retarded by the late
 going into aestivation of the previous season, and by the damp soil and lack of drying sun and wind.
 <Node id="8053"/>On May 4 the first young were observed on the southwest slopes<Node id="8115"/>.<Node id="8116"/> On
 the Ioth of May careful observations were made along the northeast slope for half a mile, on a long hill about 200 feet high. This slope was covered with wild bunch grass and balsam root, with here and there patches of wild rose and snowberry brush Symphoricarpos albus, a natural habitat for squirrels. Although many wild adult squirrels were whistling, probably females near the brood nests, only two young were seen and these were low down at the bottom of the hill. Undoubtedly the long continued blanket of snow which lay along
 the northeast hillside about two weeks longer than on the southwest slope had its influence on the activities of both plant and animal life. At this date
 the young seemed to be pretty well scattered on the southwest slope, at least there were no cases where two or more squirrels were seen at the same hole,
 an indication that they had been out of the brood nests for many days. On May i8 the young were all scattered on the southwest slope, and numerous young were found on the northeast side. On the latter they were still bunched about the holes, showing that they had come up from their under- ground nest only within the past day or two.
 The winter of I9I2-I9I3, is locally known as the winter of the "big
 snow," for during January 48.5 inches, February I0.5 inches and March I5 inches of snow fell, or a total of 74 inches. Much of this, wind driven, piled deeply on the northeast slope and remained there until May I, a condition un- doubtedly affecting the squirrels and their activities. <Node id="9656"/>The first squirrel ap- peared from hibernation on the southwest slope on February 2I, and the first one on the northeast slope was not recorded until March I3.<Node id="9815"/>
 The first signs of rutting on the southwest slopes were noticed March I5,
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
 April, 125 SEASONAL DIFFERENCES i6i
 or nearly a month after the first squirrel was out of hibernation. Even as
 late as March 29 there was little rutting activity on the northeast slope owing
 to the cold rain and deep piles of snow. It was evident, however, that on the
 southwest slope some at least had not bred, because a non-pregnant female
 was taken here as late as March 20 or 2I. This in contrast to a pregnant
 female taken March 7, I9I4.
 This year (09Q3) the young were first noted on the southwest slope on May IO. On May I7 they were very numerous on the southwest slope, where
 they had begun to scatter, and were beginning to dig in the dens for them-
 selves, an evidence of their having been out some time. Yet on this same
 date no young were out on the northeast hill sides, although the adults, pre-
 sumably females, were giving the call note which they make when their
 brood nest is approached.
 In regard to their going into aestivation, the deep snow and consequent
 late spring of I9I3 had its influence, and we find them still out on the iith of
 August, and on the I2th they were noted as abundant. These observations
 contrast strongly with those of i9io, during the preceding winter of which
 only 29 inches of snow fell for January and February and none at all in
 March, producing an early summer season and a corresponding early aestiva-
 tion. They had all disappeared by July 29.
 Further observations relative to this subject were shown especially in the
 <Node id="11511"/>summer of I9I5, when on July 26, while trapping wild squirrels, it was found
 that those of the southwest slopes had nearly all gone into aestivation.
 Scarcely a squirrel was to be seen,<Node id="11698"/> although some of their burrows showed
 signs of use. Even in the midst of a six-acre tract of spring wheat and oats, still quite green and fresh, they were disappearing. On this southwest slope, after much careful work,<Node id="11918"/> a large male was trapped on the 28th. This was the
 last one taken, and none was even seen after the 3Ist.<Node id="12025"/> On the 28th, the traps were changed to an opposite northeast slope, less than a quarter of a mile away. Here the squirrels were still out and feeding on the wheat and oats bordering this wild side hill. In a day or two after setting the traps, squir- rels began to be taken, fourteen in all, from July 26 to 3I inclusive. The
 weather was very hot and dry, the thermometer standing at 99 degrees F. on July 2ist, and the total rainfall being only .77 inches for the entire month.
 It will be seen by studying the data for these years that there is undoubt- edly considerable range in the movement of the animals living on the different slopes, <Node id="12670"/>all of the activities under consideration being from six to ten days earlier on the southwest slope.<Node id="12770"/> Perhaps the most influential factor in deter- mining the variation of these activities is the presence of heavy fall of snow and subsequent drifting which renders the northeast slopes much less habit- able for greater periods of time than the opposite southwest slope. This observation would naturally lead to the further thought that the yearly range of squirrels must be more or less restricted, even if they do seem to have a
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
 i62 WILLIAM T. SHAW Ecology, Vol. VI, No. 2
 brief migration following the breaking up of the families. In answer to
 this it might be said that still further observations of the life history have led to the belief that so finely are the activities of the animal adjusted to sur-
 rounding conditions of environment and plant growth that even the difference of a few days of awakening produces changes of food and time of breeding
 that affect subsequent activities for the entire season, thus binding them
 somewhat to their own limited locality.
 SUMMARY
 The region in southeastern Washington, especially about Pullman, has a rolling surface with a general northeast and southwest slope, with irregularly placed hills of two to three hundred feet elevation.
 The northeastern surface of these slopes is frequently piled with drifting
 snow which remains much later than on the southwest slopes, producing a
 retarded development of plant life and a consequent late activity of the
 Columbian ground squirrel.
 Other factors which would tend to retard activity would be the presence of moisture produced by melting snow and the lack of a full day's sunshine.
 As a consequence of this difference the <Node id="14528"/>animals of the northeast slope ap- pear from hibernation about ten days later than those of the southwest slope.
 They breed later by a corresponding amount of time, develop the young ac-
 cordingly, and return to aestivation in keeping with their other retarded activities.<Node id="14802"/>
This content downloaded from 205.208.116.24 on Thu, 17 Jun 2021 16:24:27 UTCAll use subject to https://about.jstor.org/terms
	Contents
	157
	158
	159
	160
	161
	162
	Issue Table of Contents
	Ecology, Vol. 6, No. 2 (Apr., 1925), pp. 93-197
	Front Matter
	Ecological Aspects of the Deserts of California [pp. 93-103]
	Effects of Oxygen and Carbon Dioxide on the Development of the Whitefish [pp. 104-116]
	Tropical Cyclones from an Ecological Viewpoint [pp. 117-122]
	Ecological Studies on Aquatic Insects. III. Adaptations of Caddisfly Larvae to Swift Streams [pp. 123-137]
	Tillage and Weeds [pp. 138-142]
	Soil Water of the New Jersey Coast [pp. 143-149]
	Factors Influencing the Distribution of Tree Vegetation in Champaign County, Illinois [pp. 150-156]
	The Seasonal Differences of North and South Slopes in Controlling the Activities of the Columbian Ground Squirrel [pp. 157-162]
	Plant Relations in Brazos County, Texas, with Special Reference to Eastern and Western Types [pp. 163-170]
	A New Device for Taking Maximum and Minimum Soil Temperatures in Forest Investigations [pp. 171-178]
	Reviews
	Review: Flower-Visiting Insects and the Reflection of Ultraviolet by Flowers [pp. 179-181]
	Review: Effect of Grazing on Native Vegetation [pp. 181-183]
	Review: Root Behavior Under Irrigation [pp. 183-184]
	Proceedings: Business Meetings of the Ecological Society of America in Washington, D. C. [pp. 185-192]
	Review: Zoological Literature [pp. 193-196]
	Notes and Comment
	Glacier Bay, Alaska, Proclaimed a National Monument by the President [p. 197]
	Back Matter
</TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
<Annotation Id="224" Type="rare to common continuum" StartNode="11511" EndNode="11698">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="225" Type="last date observation" StartNode="11918" EndNode="12025">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="226" Type="range" StartNode="12670" EndNode="12770">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="227" Type="main finding" StartNode="14528" EndNode="14802">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="218" Type="phenology" StartNode="5103" EndNode="5129">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="219" Type="time series" StartNode="6774" EndNode="7385">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="220" Type="first date observation" StartNode="6926" EndNode="6953">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="221" Type="first date observation" StartNode="8053" EndNode="8115">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="222" Type="phenology" StartNode="8053" EndNode="8116">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="223" Type="first date observation" StartNode="9656" EndNode="9815">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet Name="Original markups">
<Annotation Id="217" Type="mean" StartNode="6171" EndNode="6204">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="215" Type="Objective" StartNode="4996" EndNode="5310">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
