<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<GateDocument version="3">
<!-- The document's features-->

<GateDocumentFeatures>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">DC:TITLE</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">gate.SourceURL</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">file:/Users/anastasiabernat/Desktop/group_corpus/2018%20-%20Citizen%20Data%20and%20Trust%20in%20Official%20Statistics.pdf</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">TIKA_META:AUTHOR</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">Evelyn Ruppert ; Francisca Grommé ; Funda Ustek-Spilda ; Baki Cakici</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">TIKA_DC:CREATOR</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">Evelyn Ruppert ; Francisca Grommé ; Funda Ustek-Spilda ; Baki Cakici</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">DC:CREATOR</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">Evelyn Ruppert ; Francisca Grommé ; Funda Ustek-Spilda ; Baki Cakici</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">MimeType</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">application/pdf</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">TIKA_DC:TITLE</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics</Value>
</Feature>
<Feature>
  <Name className="java.lang.String">META:AUTHOR</Name>
  <Value className="java.lang.String">Evelyn Ruppert ; Francisca Grommé ; Funda Ustek-Spilda ; Baki Cakici</Value>
</Feature>
</GateDocumentFeatures>
<!-- The document content area with serialized nodes -->

<TextWithNodes><Node id="0"/>Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics<Node id="45"/>
Economie et Statistique /Economics and Statistics
Citizen Data and Trust in Official StatisticsEvelyn Ruppert, Francisca Grommé, Funda Ustek-Spilda, Baki Cakici
AbstractFrom smartphones, meters, fridges and cars to internet platforms, the data of digital technologies are the data of citizens.<Node id="339"/>In addition to<Node id="353"/> raising political and ethical issues of privacy, confidentiality and data protection<Node id="438"/>, this calls for rethinkingrelations to citizens in the production of data for statistics if they are to be trusted by citizens.<Node id="566"/> We outline an approach thatinvolves co-producing data with citizens as partners of statistical production, from the design of a data production platformto the interpretation and analysis of data. While raising issues such as data quality and reliability, we argue co-productioncan potentially mitigate problems associated with the re-purposing of Big Data. <Node id="924"/>We argue that in a time of “ alternativefacts”, what constitutes legitimate knowledge and expertise are major political sites of contention and struggle and requiregoing beyond defending existing practices towards inventing new ones.<Node id="1157"/> In this context, we contend that<Node id="1190"/> the future ofofficial statistics not only depends on inventing new data sources and methods but also mobilising the possibilities ofdigital technologies to establish new relations with citizens<Node id="1384"/>.
Citer ce document / Cite this document :
Ruppert Evelyn, Grommé Francisca, Ustek-Spilda Funda, Cakici Baki. Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics. In:
Economie et Statistique / Economics and Statistics, n°505-506, <Node id="1608"/>2018<Node id="1612"/>. Big Data and Statistics (Part 1) pp. 171-184;
doi : 10.24187/ecostat.2018.505d.1971
https://www.persee.fr/doc/estat_0336-1454_2018_num_505_1_10875
Fichier pdf généré le 22/08/2019
https://www.persee.fr
https://www.persee.fr/collection/estat
https://www.persee.fr/collection/estat
https://www.persee.fr/doc/estat_0336-1454_2018_num_505_1_10875
https://www.persee.fr/authority/833547
https://www.persee.fr/authority/833549
https://www.persee.fr/authority/833550
https://www.persee.fr/authority/833551
https://www.persee.fr/doc/estat_0336-1454_2018_num_505_1_10875
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 171
Citizen Data and Trust in Official StatisticsEvelyn Ruppert*, Francisca Grommé,* Funda Ustek‑Spilda**  and Baki Cakici***
Abstract – From smartphones, meters, fridges and cars to internet platforms, the data of digi‑tal technologies are the data of citizens. In addition to raising political and ethical issues of privacy, confidentiality and data protection, this calls for rethinking relations to citizens in the production of data for statistics if they are to be trusted by citizens. We outline an approach that involves co‑producing data with citizens as partners of statistical production, from the design of a data production platform to the interpretation and analysis of data. While raising issues such as data quality and reliability, we argue co‑production can potentially mitigate problems associated with the re‑purposing of Big Data. We argue that in a time of “alternative facts”, what consti‑tutes legitimate knowledge and expertise are major political sites of contention and struggle and require going beyond defending existing practices towards inventing new ones. In this context, we contend that the future of official statistics not only depends on inventing new data sources and methods but also mobilising the possibilities of digital technologies to establish new rela‑tions with citizens. 
JEL Classification: A14, C93, O35, O38 Keywords: citizen science, co‑production, experimentalism, privacy‑by‑design, smart statistics
Reminder:
The opinions and analyses in this article  are those of the author(s) and do not  necessarily reflect  their institution’s  or Insee’s views.
To cite this article: Ruppert, E., Grommé, F., Ustek‑Spilda, F. &amp; Cakici, B. (2018). Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics. Economie et Statistique / Economics and Statistics, 505‑506, 179–193.https://doi.org/10.24187/ecostat.2018.505d.1971
* Department of Sociology, Goldsmiths University of London (E.Ruppert@gold.ac.uk; F.Gromme@gold.ac.uk)** Department of Media and Communications, London School of Economics (f.ustek-spilda@lse.ac.uk)*** Technologies in Practice, IT University of Copenhagen (bakc@itu.dk)
We would like to thank two anonymous reviewers for their comments and suggestions. We are also grateful for the support and involvement of numerous national and international statisticians who made this research possible at the UK Office for National Statistics, Statistics Netherlands, Statistics Estonia, Turkish Statistical Institute, Statistics Finland, Eurostat and UNECE. Funding from a European Research Council (ERC, Consolidator Grant – Agreement n° 615588) supported the writing of this article. Principal Investigator, Evelyn Ruppert, Goldsmiths, University of London.
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018172
National Statistical Institutes (NSI) experi‑ments concerning the potential of Big Data generated by various digital technologies as a new source for the making of official statistics have now been underway for about five years. These have led to the identification of several concerns such as<Node id="5314"/> data access, data ownership, privacy and ethics, data representativeness, data quality and so on<Node id="5411"/>. Amongst other things, these concerns are understood as potential risks to the reputation and public image of NSIs work‑ing with Big Data sources, as identified in a report of the UNECE Big Data Privacy task team (UNECE, 2014).<Node id="5639"/> That report summarised a number of strategies to mitigate <Node id="5698"/>such risks including the enforcement of ethical princi‑ples through instruments of accountability and informed consent; establishing strong compli‑ance controls; developing monitoring systems to track reputational threats; ensuring transpar‑ency and understanding through clear commu‑nication with stakeholders about the use of data and the organisation of dialogues with the pub‑lic; and creating a crisis communication plan<Node id="6123"/>.<Node id="6124"/> The report also argued, as have others produced by international bodies such as Eurostat’s Big Data Task Force, that repurposing Big Data sources not only presents technical challenges but potentially could undermine citizens’ trust in how NSIs generate data and produce official statistics.<Node id="6416"/> Similar challenges are encountered when NSIs seek to repurpose administrative data generated by other government depart‑ments, which has introduced not only technical challenges but for some NSIs also raised con‑cerns about how data is shared, joined up and used for purposes other than for what they were originally generated.<Node id="6744"/>
Of course, questions of citizen trust in official statistics are not new. While trust is also a con‑cern in relation to other stakeholders including ministries, government agencies, media, uni‑versities, and other public or private research organisations that rely on official statistics, it is trust in relation to citizens that concerns us here. <Node id="7093"/>The history of established methods of generating social and population statistics, such as census questionnaires, surveys and time dia‑ries demonstrates that elaborate practices have been required to secure citizens’ trust in how data is generated and used for official statis‑tics.<Node id="7375"/> <Node id="7376"/>Through practices such as focus groups, the pilot testing of questions, and consulta‑tions with civic organisations about issues of consent, data protection, privacy, impartiality and professional standards, NSIs have sought to secure the trust of citizens <Node id="7633"/>(Struijs et al., 
2014, p. 2). Understood in this way, trust is not the result of one but myriad practices through which the trustworthiness of official statistics is accomplished.
<Node id="7814"/>Big Data<Node id="7822"/>, because it is generated not by  governments but private corporations such as platform owners, if used for official statistics could undermine these practices and the trust they have relatively well performed.<Node id="8032"/> As some statisticians have noted, “[of] critical impor‑tance is the implication of any use of Big Data for the public perception of a NSI as this has a direct impact on trust in official statistics” (Struijs et al., 2014, p. 3). While Struijs et al. argue that such risks can be mitigated by other practices such as “being transparent about what and how Big Data sources are used”, we suggest that while necessary this would be insufficient due to <Node id="8481"/>another significant issue: the repurposing of Big Data for official statistics constitutes a break and detachment in the relation between NSIs and citizens.<Node id="8637"/> While not without problems, established methods such as those noted above have involved more‑or‑less direct relations <Node id="8756"/>between NSIs and citizens to secure data as a collective accomplishment and social good.<Node id="8844"/> These relations enable citizens to be relatively active in their identification such as how they translate their knowledge and experiences into responses to questions<Node id="9011"/> and, we suggest, in turn contribute to accomplishing trust in and the legitimacy of official statistics.<Node id="9116"/>
<Node id="9117"/>This proposition was initially put forward in the “Socialising Big Data” project, which involved collaborative workshops with national and international statisticians and led to a proposal for a social framework for Big Data (Ruppert et al., 2015).<Node id="9365"/> The framework posited models of<Node id="9397"/> social ownership that stress sharing, collab‑orative, and co‑operative possibilities<Node id="9482"/> and<Node id="9486"/> that imagine Big Data as a social and collective rather than private resource.<Node id="9565"/> <Node id="9566"/>The approach that we develop in this article builds on this aspira‑tion to develop the concept of “citizen data” as a form of “re‑attachment” and social ownership that establishes new relations<Node id="9759"/> with citizens as  co‑producers of data for official statistics rather than as ever more distant subjects whose impres‑sions and confidence need to be managed.<Node id="9918"/>
We contend that this understanding of new relations is critical in two ways. First, unlike some uses of the term that define citizen data as data about citizens, our conception recog‑nises that Big Data and citizens are insepara‑ble: the data of digital technologies is the data 
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 173
Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics
of citizens. <Node id="10330"/>Second, relations that involve more direct engagements with citizens are necessary to address another consequence of detachment when data such as that generated by social media, mobile phones and browsers is repur‑posed: the risk of a widening gap between  citizens’ actions, identifications and expe‑riences and how they are categorised, included and excluded in statistics, the interpretation of that data, and citizens’ identifications with the resulting statistics.<Node id="10799"/>1 We refer to this risk as a widening gap because these consequences are not entirely new or limited to Big Data.2 Former Eurostat Director General Walter Radermacher expressed this more generally as a<Node id="11000"/> gap between citizen experiences and official statistics which in turn calls for “subjective statistics”<Node id="11104"/>.3 In saying so he stressed the need for<Node id="11144"/> a more <Node id="11152"/>democratic debate between citizens and data producers and owners to achieve a “more subjective, differ‑entiated understanding of our world”<Node id="11291"/>, instead of “technocrats and politicians sitting together and confronting citizens in the end”<Node id="11386"/>.4 For our  concept of citizen data this requires processes of <Node id="11449"/>co‑production that involve direct relations with citizens in the production of data for making official statistics<Node id="11563"/>. 
Our argument draws on<Node id="11587"/> several years of field‑work conducted at NSIs and international sta‑tistical organisations (see Box; see also the working paper by Grommé et al., 2017). This research led to the identification of four prin‑ciples for citizen data that started from key  “matters of concern” statisticians have expressed about the future of official statistics <Node id="11931"/>
which we encountered in our fieldwork. We consider these as matters of concern for two rea‑sons. First, to recognise them as normativities that influence and guide statisticians’ actions and development of practical solutions 1234(Boltanski  &amp; Chiapello, 2007). Second, to engage in a form of critique that does not dismiss the con‑cepts of our research subjects but first engages with how they conceive and define concepts to then consider how concepts can be reconceived (Latour, 2004). That is, taking up the concerns statisticians have expressed does not mean  to agree with them and their assumptions but to engage with and then reconceive those con‑cerns. <Node id="12594"/>The four matters of concern we identified as significant to our concept of citizen data are experimentalism, citizen science, smart sta‑tistics and privacy‑by‑design.<Node id="12760"/> In the next part of this article we introduce each concern and then draw on a range of literature in the social sciences to reconceive each and then express them as principles of citizen data. Central to our 
1. For example, experiments with mobile phone data to model mobility encounter problems when attempting to interpret the meaning of travel patterns. 2. <Node id="13122"/>We are aware that issues of representation also affect established sta-tistical methods. GDP, Gross Domestic Product, for instance, is one such highly debated official statistic. Columbia University economist Joseph Stiglitz draws attention to how GDP has come to be ”fetishised” as ”the” indicator of how well a national economy is doing, despite various short-comings (Stiglitz et al., 2009).<Node id="13516"/> <Node id="13517"/>Consequently, Fleurbaey (2009) suggests moving ”beyond GDP” and draws attention to other approaches, including recent developments in the analysis of sustainability, happiness and the theory of social choice and fair allocation to the studies of social welfare.<Node id="13778"/> Similar arguments have also been raised for employment indicators, espe-cially with respect to people working in non-regular employment arrange-ments (see Hussmanns, 2004).3.<Node id="13953"/> <Node id="13954"/>Fieldwork notes, Eurostat conference "Towards More Agile Social Statistics",<Node id="14030"/> Luxembourg, 28-30 November 2016.4. Idem.
Box – The research project 
<Node id="14100"/>Our concept of citizen data comes from several years of ethnographic fieldwork that we conducted at five NSIs and two international statistical organisations, which involved observing conferences and meetings, follow‑ing and analysing publications, and conducting inter‑views and engaging in conversations with statisticians.<Node id="14425"/> More precisely, this article builds on and summarises key points in an ARITHMUS working paper by Grommé et al. (2017). ARITHMUS (Peopling Europe: How data make a people), an ERC funded project, began in 2014 with a team of six researchers: Evelyn Ruppert (Principal Investigator), Baki Cakici, Francisca Grommé, Stephan Scheel, and Funda Ustek‑Spilda (Postdoctoral Researchers), and Ville Takala (Doctoral Researcher). We followed working practices at five NSIs (UK Office for National Statistics, Statistics Netherlands, Statistics Estonia, Turkish Statistical Institute, and Statistics Finland) and two international organisations (Eurostat and UNECE). Amongst other things, we followed 
statisticians’ debates about and experiments with digital technologies and big data and their implications for offi‑cial statistics. Based on this fieldwork we conducted two workshops with a project advisory group of statisticians to discuss some of our analyses such as the changing relations between NSIs and citizens as a consequence of new digital technologies and big data sources. This led to a working paper that summarised some of the arguments outlined in this article and introduced the con‑cept of citizen data, which was reviewed by the advisory group (Grommé et al., 2017).<Node id="15702"/> That review led to a collab‑orative workshop with the advisory group and a broader group of statisticians, academic researchers, information designers and facilitators on the development of design principles for the co‑production of an app for citizen data. <Node id="15961"/>Rather than summarising empirical material from our ethnography and the workshops, our objective here is to outline the conception of citizen data that we have developed as a result of this research.
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018174
re‑conception is that the future of official sta‑tistics not only depends on working with new digital technologies, data sources and inventing methods, but on establishing new relations to citizens (Ruppert, 2018).
We have intended this discussion of a concept of citizen data principally for statisticians but also for social science researchers for three key rea‑sons. One is that we have brought concepts and understandings advanced in the social sciences to bear on matters of concern expressed by statisti‑cians. In this way, we contribute more generally to social science research methods. <Node id="16829"/>Another reason is that the principles and concept of citizen data also apply to debates within the social sciences concerning research methods that engage with digital technologies and Big Data sources.<Node id="17031"/> That is, while the issues and objectives of social  science research are different, relations to citizens in the production of knowledge are a shared con‑cern. <Node id="17192"/>Third, as reflected in our research method which involved workshops with statisticians, a concept of citizen data calls for experimen‑tal engagements not only with citizens but also between social scientists and statisticians.<Node id="17418"/>
Experimentalism 
The first matter of concern that we have come across in our fieldwork is experimentalism. Government agencies and corporations have embraced experimentation as a necessary part of innovation. Official statistics is a good  example as attested by the development of <Node id="17701"/>inno‑vation laboratories, sandboxes, hackathons and exploratory research projects.5 For statisticians, experiments with new digital technologies and Big Data are methods to develop new ways of thinking, techniques, and skills<Node id="17926"/> in the produc‑tion of official statistics. There are also various strands within the social sciences that engage with experimentalism. Relatively new, however, is the adoption of experimenting as a method  <Node id="18133"/>to open scientific and technological expertise to different actors to generate new ways of think‑ing<Node id="18233"/>. In areas as diverse as wheelchair design, Big Data and synthetic biology, social scientists have adopted experimentalism to generate new spaces of problem formulation, engage with different actors and consider different possibili‑ties.6 That is, a key premise is that experimental modes of collaboration can generate new ways of thinking.
Broadly speaking, we can distinguish two mod‑els through which collaborative experiments 
may seek to achieve this. <Node id="18690"/>The first is through var‑ious forms of participation intended to achieve a degree of democratisation by opening up scien‑tific and technical debates and processes to publics (Marres, 2012). The second is to experi‑ment collaboratively to develop and explore new problem formulations, transcend ingrained styles of reasoning, disrupt existing hierar‑chies and critically examine how knowledge is created (Rabinow &amp; Bennett, 2012).<Node id="19119"/> This is  the model of a “collaborator” (or, co‑laboratory)  where participants engage in the common exploration of a topic. The Socialising Big Data project previously mentioned engaged with this model by conducting workshops and discus‑sions with national statisticians, genomic scien‑tists and waste management engineers to define and develop shared concepts for understanding Big Data (Ruppert et al., 2015). <Node id="19532"/>Another form of collaboration involves the co‑production of a “thing” – a tangible end‑product – through which collaborators practically explore and develop shared concepts and issues.<Node id="19716"/> Working on a common product makes “issues experimen‑tally available to such an extent that “the pos‑sible” becomes tangible, formable, and within reach” (Binder et al., 2015, p. 12). <Node id="19900"/>As a method, it forces participants to make future modes of working explicit (Muniesa &amp; Linhardt, 2011). <Node id="20005"/>Generally, from the social studies of science we learn that such collaborative experiments also require reshaping relations between partici‑pants, technologies and knowledge. <Node id="20180"/>This is also a principle of what is called in the social sciences and humanities, practice‑based research, which involves an engagement between partici‑pants and the skills, materials, small tasks and everyday labour, in addition to texts and spo‑ken word, that are enrolled in making things (Jungnickel, 2017). <Node id="20492"/>Making things, as opposed to unravelling or deconstructing them, involves a close entanglement with different participants and can increase understanding of the skills, relations and infrastructures that are part of an end‑product (ibid.).56

5. See for example, experimental statistics produced by Eurostat: http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/web/experimental-statistics/.6. For these three examples, see: https://entornoalasilla.wordpress.com/english/; Ruppert et al., 2015; and http://www.anthropos-lab.net/about.
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 175
Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics

Experimentalism is especially recognised as a necessary approach to uncertainty and change. <Node id="21214"/>For example, in an article on a collaboration between academics, farmers and environmenta‑lists,<Node id="21310"/> Waterton and Tsouvalis (2015, p. 477) ask how “the politics of nature can be envi‑sioned for an age conscious of the complexity, contingency, and relationality of the world?”<Node id="21485"/> <Node id="21486"/>They investigate a collaboration between them‑selves as social scientists with environmental experts and farmers to improve water quality. In their experience, a shared inquiry opened up questions of how to understand water pollu‑tion: in terms of isolated causes or wider socio‑ technical relations and histories. <Node id="21801"/>They thus adopted an agenda of experimentation that understands the generation of knowledge as involving “hybrid forums” (Callon et al., 2011) or “new collectives” (Latour, 2006)<Node id="21979"/> in which participants reflexively engage in reconstructing the relations, histories and stakeholders involved in an issue. Uncertainty is not something to be solved, instead it needs to be acknowledged and worked with in an ongoing collective pro‑cess of <Node id="22235"/>knowledge production. In practice this entails a “care‑full” approach (Grommé, 2015) which entails the exercise of responsibilities for monitoring and documenting who and what are (unavoidably) included and excluded; avoid‑ing ambiguity about the terms of evaluation by making explicit how outcomes are assessed; recognising that failure is likely caused by my‑ riad factors; and, understanding that values are inseparable from facts.<Node id="22669"/> “Care‑full” therefore does not only refer to a cautious approach, but also active acknowledgement that experiments continually reshape relations and redistribute effects in sometimes unexpected ways.
As a principle of citizen data, experimentalism thus involves not only experimenting but col‑laborating to make ways of thinking and gene‑rating knowledge “open” to the influence and insights of others and in doing so imagining and speculating on alternatives and possibilities (Stengers, 2010). It requires being accountable to and accounting for the procedures and prac‑tices of experiments. <Node id="23264"/>Finally, it means being open to how relations between different par‑ticipants in the making of knowledge might be organised differently.<Node id="23400"/> Taking up our point on new relations between citizens and NSIs, expe‑rimentalism thus involves active and open forms of participation and influence. We develop this further through a second principle, that of citi‑zen science, to explore how relations between NSIs and citizens in the making of data and offi‑cial statistics might further be reconceived.
Citizen Science
Some statistical organisations have started experimenting with models of citizen engage‑ment in the production of data. Such models 
often draw on existing conceptions of citizen science, which we will briefly discuss here to explore how we might reconceive them. <Node id="24036"/>Different models of citizen science conceive of citizens as not only research subjects, but as actively involved in the production of data as opposed to traditional methods where they are usually understood as respondents.<Node id="24258"/> There are many definitions and interpretations of citizen science and the terms of citizen engagement in the making of data. <Node id="24384"/>The European Commission (EC), for example, defines it as the “production of knowledge beyond the scope of professional science, often referred to as lay, local and tra‑ditional knowledge” (European Commission, 2013, p. 5)<Node id="24605"/>. <Node id="24607"/>Goodchild (2007) uses the term to describe communities or networks of citi‑zens who act as observers in some domain of science.<Node id="24734"/> This is the most commonly accepted definition especially evident in the significant momentum citizen science has gained in the natural sciences in recent years (Kullenberg &amp; Kasperowski, 2016, p. 2).<Node id="24934"/> However, the prac‑tice of engaging people in collecting and sub‑mitting data for scientific purposes goes back at least to the 1960s, though the term itself was not used until the 1990s (ibid.).7<Node id="25130"/>
<Node id="25131"/>A second version involves citizens not as only observers but co‑producers or producers of scientific studies and data to reflect their own concerns, needs and questions. This version includes local and activist‑oriented approaches referred to as “community based auditing”, “civic science”, “community environmental policing”, “street science”, “popular epidemi‑ology”, “crowd science”, and “Do It Yourself Science” (Kullenberg &amp; Kasperowski 2016, p. 2)<Node id="25584"/>. These versions range from citizens seek‑ing close alliances with scientific and know‑ledge institutions to citizens engaging in the production of independent knowledge together with scientists. 
Citizens’ objectives for engaging in scientific data production are multiple, ranging from documenting concerns about environmental issues, to creating online archival maps of local historical sites or transcribing Shakespearean contemporaries.8 Goodchild (2007, p. 219) suggests that people who generally participate and share information on the internet are more likely to volunteer geographic information and 
7. For some researchers, it includes the <Node id="26235"/>National Audubon Society’s Annual Christmas Bird Count in early 1900s<Node id="26304"/>, where citizens participated in the observation and enumeration of bird species.8. Some of these examples are documented at www.zooniverse.org.
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018176
contribute to <Node id="26535"/>data collection initiatives such as OpenStreetMap (OSM)<Node id="26590"/>. On this basis he argues that two kinds of people are likely to participate: people who seek self‑promotion and volunteer personal information on the internet to make it “available to friends and relations, irrespective of the fact that it becomes available to all”; and, people who seek personal satisfaction derived from contributing anonymous information and seeing it appear as part of a developing “patch‑work” of collective contributions (ibid., p. 219).
<Node id="27052"/>Jasanoff (2003) notes that models of citizen  science can facilitate meaningful interaction  among policymakers, scientific experts, corpo‑rate producers and publics (pp. 235–236).<Node id="27232"/> She argues that the pressure for accountability in expert decision‑making is manifest in the demand for greater transparency and wider par‑ticipation. However, participatory opportunities cannot alone ensure the representative and dem‑ocratic governance of science and technology. Jasanoff underscores that the attention of mod‑ern states has focused on refining “technologies of hubris” that are designed to facilitate manage‑ment and control by bracketing off uncertainty, political objections and the unforeseen complex‑ities of everyday life (p. 238). <Node id="27789"/>What is lacking is not just knowledge, but ways to bring uncer‑tain, unknown processes and methods into the dynamics of democratic debate (pp. 239–240).<Node id="27941"/>  For this reason Jasanoff suggests citizen science as a possible model of democratic interaction between different stakeholders in the production of science. In this way citizen science models can be thought of as “technologies of humi lity”, that is, social technologies that involve rela‑tions between governments, decision‑makers,  experts, and citizens <Node id="28299"/>in the management of technology for “assessing the unknown and the uncertain, ‘modest assessments’” that engage citizens as active agents of knowledge, insight, and memory<Node id="28470"/> (p. 243; italics in the original).
One concern with the role of non‑scientists in the production of science are the implications for established scientific principles.9 However, as Goodchild (2007) demonstrates, while strictly speaking citizen science might not  fulfil scientific criteria per se, it can potentially open up new ways of thinking and approaching data. This is especially relevant for practices of democratisation, which call for different forms of reasoning, as captured in <Node id="28961"/>Herbert Simon’s (1947) conception of “satisficing” rather than “optimizing” or “maximizing” in decision‑ making.<Node id="29073"/> In opposition to abstractions such as  utility theory he advanced an understanding 
based on how people reason in practice. Practical reason ing, he argued, involves juggling nume‑rous criteria and arriving at a “good enough”  solution rather than engaging in an infinite search for all possible ones, evaluating them and then arri ving at the best one. <Node id="29428"/>Gabrys &amp; Pritchard (2015) take a similar approach to suggest that the adequacy of an answer depends on how practi‑cal questions are posed.<Node id="29566"/> Instead, they define “just good enough data” to counter the reliance on measurement accuracy as the only objec‑tive and criterion for evaluating environmental data gathered through citizen sensing practices. Measurements of environmental phenomena meet different objectives or questions, which are often not known in advance. For instance, a “rough” measurement to identify a pollution event when it is happening or when it has hap‑pened might be sufficient and “good‑enough”. <Node id="30044"/>What Gabrys &amp; Pritchard draw attention to is that the potential uses or value of data are often not known in advance and that there is value in organising data production and interpretation as practices of searching for potential rather than reiterating and replicating already known  objectives or questions through previously established methods.<Node id="30392"/>9
Recent experiments by statistical organisations with models of citizen engagement include a pilot project by Statistics Canada using OSM for crowdsourcing citizen work to help fill in data gaps on geolocations (Statistics Canada, 2016).10 <Node id="30633"/>OSM is a collaborative initiative designed to create a free and editable map of the world.<Node id="30723"/> The application for Statistics Canada allows users to select a geolocation and edit, for instance, the name of a street. Another exam‑ple is from the <Node id="30874"/>European Commission’s Joint Research Centre on Citizen Science and Open Data which has explored possible models of citizen engagement for monitoring the spread of invasive alien plant species (IAS) (Cardoso et al., 2017). That report argued that the imple‑mentation of the IAS Regulation<Node id="31161"/> could benefit from the contributions of citizens in providing “accurate, detailed, and timely information on IAS occurrences and distribution for efficient prevention, early detection, rapid response, and to allow for evaluation of management measures” (p. 5). Additionally, this form of citizen engagement could raise awareness and increase public support for the regulation as 
9. Also see Gabrys et al. (2016) for discussions about data quality and credibility.10. The pilot was organized by Statistics Canada in collaboration with OpenNorth, MapBox, City of Ottawa and OSM Canada. OpenNorth is a non-profit organization developing digital tools for civic engagement.
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 177
Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics
well as supporting citizens in acquiring skills and better understanding of scientific work (Socientize Consortium, 2014). The United Nations has also identified citizen science data production on environmental issues as neces‑sary to the measurement and monitoring of <Node id="32220"/>sustainable development goals (SDGs) (United Nations, 2016). Modes of citizen engagement are recognised as key to ensuring that the 2030 Agenda for Sustainable Development is  country‑owned and context specific and with goals linked to national values and priorities.<Node id="32487"/> <Node id="32488"/>While these initiatives conceive of citizen engagement in varying ways, they generally limit it to tasks such as data production, verifica‑tion and classification. This has led to criticisms  of these forms of citizen science as exploitative of citizens as free public labour (DataShift, n.d.; Piovesan, 2017; Paul, 2018). <Node id="32811"/>What they point to is that tasks related to data cleaning, coding or analysis as well as design, architecture or inter‑pretation are reserved for experts while citizens are limited to being no more than research sub‑jects or assistants.
We reconceive of citizen science in a way that is more closely aligned with what Jasanoff expresses as the inclusive generation of know‑ledge. <Node id="33191"/>But, following from our argument about detachment, we suggest that inclusivity involves the right to make claims and articulate concerns about how environmental, economic and social issues should be categorised and known.<Node id="33412"/>11 Arguably, this is the claim citizen scientists make when they engage in the independent production of data to challenge or supplement official and scientific knowledge. However, our conception of citizen data envisages citizens not as independent but as co‑producers. In this way, we conceive of citizen data as involving new relations between citizens and NSIs in ways that combine statistical science and citizen  science. <Node id="33840"/>Such a conception could involve citi‑zen engagement in statistical production and lead to statistics that are more representative and inclusive of citizens’ concerns, needs and experiences, as well as their own identifications.<Node id="34067"/> As such, it would necessitate an approach that is flexible and experimental in its criteria (Paul, 2018) so that it can adapt to the shifting needs and requirements of not only citizens, but also what matters to them. As we suggest below, this includes broadening the understanding of ethics beyond consent, fairness, and data protection to what is arguably at the core of the rise of citi‑zen science: citizens as active in the making and shaping of the data through which official sta‑tistics and knowledge are generated. In the next 
section, we explore what this understanding of ethics might mean in relation to another matter of concern: proposals for “smart statistics”.
Smart Statistics
Propositions by Eurostat for the development of “smart statistics” build on conceptions of “smart cities”, usually understood as the use of Big Data, urban sensors, Internet of Things (IoT) and other forms of data production and data integration to streamline municipal governance and transportation infrastructures, rejuvenate local economies, transform the urban environ‑ment to make it more sustainable, liveable, and socially inclusive (see for instance Henriquez, 2016). While smart cities have been defined in various ways, the concept generally refers to on the one hand how “cities are increasingly composed of and monitored by pervasive and ubiquitous computing and, on the other, whose economy and governance is being driven by innovation, creativity and entrepreneurship, enacted by smart people” (Kitchin, 2014, p. 1). In this view, Big Data offers the possibility of real‑time analysis of city life, new modes of urban governance, and envisioning and making more efficient, sustainable, competitive, pro‑ductive, open and transparent cities. 11
Leveraging “smart systems” such as smart energy, smart meters, smart transport, and so on is an objective of proposals for “smart statistics” put forward by <Node id="35978"/>Eurostat’s Big Data Task Force. The proposals seek to engage with the potential of the proliferation of digital devices and sen‑sors connected to the internet and how the data they generate might be embedded in statistical production systems such that statistics could be produced in “real‑time” and “automatically”.12 In this view, data capturing, analysis and pro‑cessing are envisioned as embedded in activities that generate and simultaneously analyse data. The adoption of such an approach could dra‑matically transform the production system for official statistics and calls for rethinking busi‑ness processes and architectures, laws and regu‑lations, ethics, methodologies, and so on. <Node id="36670"/>
11. This is an understanding advanced in the field of critical citizenship studies and summarised in Isin &amp; Ruppert (2015) and Isin &amp; Saward (2013). <Node id="36820"/>Being a citizen is understood as a political subjectivity that includes not only the possession of rights but the right to make rights claims such as the right to shape how data is made about them and the populations of which they are being constituted as a part (Ruppert, 2018).<Node id="37099"/>12. Eurostat Big Data Task Force (2016) “Smart Statistics”. Draft docu-ment. October.
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018178
Two approaches for generating smart statis‑tics understood in this way have been pro‑posed: using third party systems that exist for other purposes than statistics but from which statistical information can be extracted (e.g., mobile phones); or developing entirely new data production practices such as sensors and digital devices exclusively for generating sta‑tistical information.13 The third‑party approach engenders many of the concerns we previously identified such as data access and ownership, privacy and ethics, data representativeness, quality, and trust as well as greater detachment between citizens and NSIs. However, the lat‑ter approach of designing new devices of data production, provides an opportunity to miti‑gate these issues. That is, we reconceive of smart statistics as not only requiring that NSIs rethink the technical and organisational aspects of statistical production systems, but also their relations to citizens. As noted in the discussion of citizen science, this could involve models of co‑production that engage citizens in the pro‑duction of smart statistics.
It would, however, mean being care‑full in the ways we previously outlined including a broader understanding of ethics that extends throughout the production of official statistics. Ethics of course have long been central prin‑ciples of official statistics, which address the values of utility, professional standards and ethics, scientific principles, transparency, qua‑lity, timeliness, costs, respondent burden, and confidentiality (UN, 2014).14 These principles constitute what we would call an ethic of care for data, such as care for the quality, accessi‑bility and clarity of data, but also for relations and accountabilities to citizens through prac‑tices such as data protection, confidentiality, consent, and trust. While the origins of these principles are a mix of legal, governmen‑tal, political and professional rationales and requirements, they tend to operate as part of everyday working values and commitments. This is evident in claims made by statisticians such as “just because you can, doesn’t mean you should” use Big Data sources.
The fundamental principles of official statistics thus express a broad conception of ethics that includes relations to citizens that social science research calls procedural ethics (Guillemin &amp; Gillam, 2004). Procedural ethics are under‑stood as an estimation of the ethical issues that might be involved when research and data pro‑duction are undertaken. However, Guillemin and Gillam note a second dimension of ethics 
in research, which they term “ethics in practice” (id., p. 261). It concerns the recurrent, iterative, and uncertain ethical moments that happen dur‑ing research and which may be odds with that covered in a procedural ethics review. This latter understanding is relevant to practices involved in the<Node id="40129"/> co‑production of smart statistics, which, by definition, involve uncertainty, adaptation and responsiveness to the interactions, interests and demands of different stakeholders. As such, co‑production demands an ethic of care that rec‑ognises and is responsive to the dependence on relations to citizens and their labours to “cre‑ate, hold together and sustain” data (Puig de la Bellacasa, 2012, p. 198).<Node id="40534"/> 1314
<Node id="40540"/>The concept of citizen data we propose thus reconceives of smart statistics as involving new relations to citizens as co‑producers of data production platforms.<Node id="40700"/> It is a conception that calls for a care‑full approach that enlarges the understanding of ethics to include the demands,  interests and contributions of citizens at diffe‑rent stages of the development of new devices of data production rather than at the backend as an afterthought or correction. As such, it is a model that builds on the <Node id="41040"/>premises of another matter of concern, <Node id="41079"/>privacy‑by‑design<Node id="41096"/>,<Node id="41097"/> which addresses issues of privacy and consent at the frontend of software design, which we address next.
Privacy‑by‑Design 
Big Data and new data sources come with new questions concerning privacy, consent and con‑fidentiality that are not always fully addressed by existing regulatory frameworks. As such,  privacy‑by‑design has become as matter of con‑cern for NSIs. Privacy‑by‑design is understood as the embedding of privacy protection at the soft‑ware design stage of data production platforms, devices or applications. It entails designing pri‑vacy protection with citizens in mind at the outset  and the implementation of these designs in a 
13. Ibid. One example is Statistics Netherlands collection of data for sta-tistics about road traffic intensities which are produced purely on the basis of road sensors. See: https://www.cbs.nl/en-gb/our-services/innovation/nieuwsberichten/recente-berichten/new-steps-in-big-data-for-traffic-and-transport-statistics.14. <Node id="42068"/>Six principles are that: official statistics must meet the test of practi-cal utility; be developed according to strictly professional considerations, scientific principles and professional ethics; present information on the scientific standards of their sources, methods and procedures; may be generated from all types of sources such as surveys or administrative records and the source chosen with regard to quality, timeliness, costs and the burden on respondents; are to be strictly confidential and used exclusively for statistical purposes; and the laws, regulations and mea-sures governing them should be public.<Node id="42687"/>
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 179
Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics
transparent manner. As such, privacy‑by‑design is a response to the problem of privacy, consent, and confidentiality through software and which can be used in tandem with other tools, such as privacy impact assessments.<Node id="43025"/> By employing  privacy‑by‑design, privacy issues are addressed at the beginning of the design process, in con‑trast to other approaches that aim at solving privacy issues after software development is complete or leave privacy considerations to legal or regulatory frameworks.<Node id="43301"/>
Cavoukian et al. (2010) define privacy‑by‑design  through seven foundational principles: proac‑tive not reactive and preventative not reactive; privacy as the default; privacy embedded into design; full functionality that leads to positive sum, not zero‑sum outcomes; end‑to‑end life‑cycle protection; visibility and transparency; and  respect for user privacy. These principles require designs to be committed to privacy from the beginning and to limit data production to ways that are respectful of citizens’ expectations. The principles also require that data production software addresses the likelihood that data may exist after the software stops functioning. <Node id="43968"/>The authors also emphasise that the lifecycle of soft‑ware must be considered when deciding on how to best protect privacy, including making plans for deleting data once the software reaches the end of its lifecycle<Node id="44183"/>. Finally, the principles com‑pel organisations dealing with personal data to be transparent in their goals and to remain accountable to citizens.
However, the production and processing of personal data present many other challenges for privacy in addition to individual pri‑vacy. Nissenbaum (2004) argues that privacy norms need to be tied to specific contexts. She describes three principles that have dom‑inated debates around privacy throughout the 20th century, namely, limiting surveillance of citizens by governments, restricting access to private information, and curtailing intrusions into private places. She suggests a new term, “contextual integrity”, to deal with the new challenges introduced by digital technologies. <Node id="44915"/>Contextual integrity demands that information gathering is kept appropriate to the context and obeys the governing norms of distribu‑tion within it. The key insight is that norms of  distribution vary across cultures, historical periods, locales, and other factors. Additionally, contextual integrity requires awareness of not only the specific site of data production but also the relevance of related social institutions (Nissenbaum, 2009).<Node id="45357"/>
Approaches that aim to protect individual pri‑vacy may still lead to undesired outcomes in large‑scale data production efforts.<Node id="45485"/> When indi‑vidually anonymised data are joined to create profiles, individuals who fit the profile could still experience effects even when they are not identified individually. For example, Graham (2005) discusses how software can be used to assign different categories to different parts of a city based on school performance, house prices, crime rates, etc., which might potentially orchestrate inequalities and discriminate inhab‑itants, even when they are not personally iden‑tified. <Node id="45974"/>Similarly, Zwitter (2014) has identified and problematised the potential discriminatory “group effects” of anonymised data such as in practices of profiling.
The use of Big Data also introduces additional privacy challenges. Barocas and Nissenbaum (2014) argue that anonymity and consent are often fundamentally undermined in Big Data applications, and that other approaches are needed to protect integrity, such as policies based on moral and political principles that serve specific contextual goals and values. Instead of focusing on anonymity in Big Data applications, they instead emphasise securing informed consent, not only as a choice for sub‑jects to waive consent or not, but a requirement that data collectors justify their actions in rela‑tion to norms, standards, and expectations. To an extent this is addressed in the recently imple‑mented <Node id="46830"/>General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) in member states across the European Union, which is based on a broad understan‑ding of personal data and privacy and will end practices of general consent by default for  the production of personal data.<Node id="47076"/>15 It introduces the requirement to think “what is personal data” for all private and public stakeholders which demand, hold or archive personal data, as well as what are the ethical practices required to deal with personal data, given the complexity and connectedness of data systems and proven non‑neutrality of algorithms. In sum, privacy is not a single thing but depends on the context of production, accountability for group effects, and mechanisms of informed consent. 
Recently, scholars working to address the technical challenges of privacy in relation to Big Data have proposed a method of privacy  protection by taking advantage of blockchain technology (Montjoye et al., 2014; Zyskind 
15. The General Data Protection Regulation came into force in May 2018. See: https://www.eugdpr.org/.
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018180
et al., 2015). Blockchain is a distributed com‑puting method where many devices communi‑cate with one another over a shared network, without requiring a central server to authorise the participation of each member or to keep a list of currently connected members. <Node id="48213"/>By applying blockchain technology to privacy, it becomes possible to encrypt and distribute private data over a large network without requiring a trusted central server.<Node id="48382"/>
Blockchain privacy methods are intended to solve underlying privacy challenges using a technical framework during software develop‑ment. However, as we have indicated above, they do not stand on their own as the sole solution to ensuring privacy, but rather supple‑ment legal and policy‑oriented considerations such as contextual integrity, group effects and modes of consent through software design. <Node id="48784"/>We thus reconceive of privacy‑by‑design beyond software to include citizen privacy as a right that should be built into not only the frontend of software design but through relations with citizens as co‑producers in the production of official statistics. <Node id="49039"/>That is, like ethics, <Node id="49061"/>privacy is processual<Node id="49082"/> and cannot be settled through the one‑time granting of consent or software design alone or independent of specific contexts. 
*  * *
In sum, we have taken up matters of concern expressed by statisticians and reconceived of them as principles of citizen data. Through the discussion of the four principles of experimen‑talism, citizen science, smart statistics and pri‑vacy‑by‑design, we have explored how citizen data can create new attachments and relations between citizens and NSIs, and between citi‑zens’ actions, identifications and experiences and how they are categorised, included and excluded in statistics. In this regard, we argue it has the potential to produce new statistical vari‑ables desired and identified by citizens,<Node id="49819"/> increase their identification with official statistics and possibly advance their role as also users of sta‑tistics. Indeed the latter may well be a collateral effect of co‑producing statistics with citizens in ways that are more in accordance with their experiences and knowledge.<Node id="50101"/>
We place the significance of our concept of citi‑zen data within the current proliferation of data 
production platforms that enable myriad data generators (e.g., platform owners) and ana‑lysts (e.g., researchers, governments, media) to produce statistics and knowledge of societies (Ruppert et al., 2013). Indeed, many topics of interest to NSIs such as price levels, the econ‑omy, consumer sentiment or tourism can be measured using Big Data generated by brow‑sers, social media or devices such as mobile phones that can be accessed and analysed by different actors.<Node id="50670"/> Some would claim that this represents a “democratisation” of knowledge and the erosion of validated knowledge and expertise about societies. However, as Ruppert et al. (2013) contend, this widening distribu‑tion of data and analysis means that knowledge of societies does not cohere in single authorita‑tive accounts to the same extent that it perhaps did in the recent past. Instead, what consti‑tutes legitimate knowledge and expertise have become major sites of political contention and struggle as revealed in current debates about “alternative facts”.<Node id="51227"/>
<Node id="51228"/>Proposals that NSIs need to thus defend the qua‑lity and legitimacy of official statistics through gatekeeping practices such as demonstrating their trustworthiness by making their statisti‑cal practices transparent and thus assessable, fact checking competing statistics, and “calling out bad numbers” certainly have a role to play.<Node id="51561"/> <Node id="51562"/>However, they potentially play into the premise that what is at stake is winning a competition of “facts”. They ignore that what constitutes “pub‐ lic facts” should be open to democratic contes‐ tation and deliberation because they inevitably involve normative judgements about social meaning and choices about which experiential realities matter (Jasanoff &amp; Simmit, 2017).<Node id="51935"/> <Node id="51936"/>We thus suggest NSIs have a role to play in fostering official statistics as social and collective accom‑plishments where their legitimacy is derived from conditions of co‑production that address data subjects as citizens with rights to be active participants. Such an approach understands data and official statistics as social technologies that require new forms of engagement and relations between experts, decision‑makers, and citizens for addressing collective problems (Jasanoff, 2003) and as matters of democratic delibera‑tion where citizens are active in the making and shaping of knowledge about societies of which they are a part.
We recognise that the concept of citizen data raises many practical and political questions. For one, we are not suggesting that existing methods and their relations to citizens will 
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 181
Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics
become obsolete. However, methods such as surveys and questionnaires will likely change as digital technologies are increasingly adopted and a concept of citizen data can possibly inform those changes. That is, beyond Big Data sources, how data is produced by NSIs using various methods can be reconceived along the lines of what we call citizen data. While online or digital surveys and censuses, for example, are being adopted they do not imagine the pos‑sibilities of co‑production. <Node id="53366"/>Different modes of co‑production could be adopted that utilise the affordances of digital technologies and poten‑tially produce data that more closely aligns with the experiences and knowledge of citizens. <Node id="53572"/>
Throughout our discussion we have defined co‑production as involving citizens in the sta‑tistical production process. What this would mean practically is of course a major question and extends to issues of representativeness and inclusion in that process. This is a matter of concern for all methods especially taking into account the heterogeneity of citizens. For me thods that mobilise digital technologies such as online censuses and surveys this is poten‑tially exacerbated by what has come to be called  the “digital divide”. These are only some of the possible practical and political issues that arise from citizen data, which we also addressed in the collaborative workshop with statisticians noted previously. While we have not reported on the outcomes of that workshop in this arti‑cle, one outcome was imagining alternative “roadmaps” for engaging with citizens at diffe‑rent stages of the statistical production process, from the co‑design of prototypes for data gene‑ration platforms and apps to the establishment  of co‑operative forms of data ownership. In other words, citizen data does call for rethinking 
statistical production processes and some of their fundamental premises.
<Node id="54771"/>For example, aspects of statistical production that would need to be rethought are those of data standards and quality.<Node id="54890"/> However, as noted, the principle of experimentalism calls for being open to such questions and not settling them in advance including what may or could constitute quality. Interestingly, this is also recog nised in NSI experiments with Big Data generated by third party systems where concerns about quality as well as others such as the represent‑ativeness of data have been raised. One solu‑tion statisticians propose is that statistics that repurpose Big Data could be adopted not as replacements but auxiliary, complementary or supplementary to existing data sources.<Node id="55461"/> While possibly relegating such data to a diffe‑rent status and role, this response provides an opportunity to rethink how statistics are made “official”. That is, it suggests that there is not one mode of production or set of standards through which data can be made official. <Node id="55739"/>We suggest that this also applies to existing methods  that produce data for official statistics but which involve myriad standards and where quality is not singularly defined or measura‑ble. <Node id="55931"/>However, the concept of citizen data that we have developed introduces a critical diffe‑rence that goes beyond issues of standards and  quality. It proposes that the authority and exper‑tise to make statistics official are not founded in a single institution, but in processes of co‑ production and direct relations to citizens. In that regard, citizen data approaches claims of “alternative facts” as not matters of accuracy and standards but of the relations to citizens through which data and in turn statistics are made official. 
BIBLIOGRAPHY
Barocas, S. &amp; Nissenbaum, H. (2014). Big Data’s End Run Around Anonymity and Consent. In Lane, J., Stodden, V. Bender, S. &amp; Nissenbaum, H. (Eds.), Privacy, Big Data, and the Public Good, pp. 44–75. Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press.
Binder, T., Brandt, E., Ehn, P. &amp; Halse, J. (2015). Democratic Design Experiments: Between Parlia‑ment and Laboratory. CoDesign, 11(3‑4), 152–165.https://doi.org/10.1080/15710882.2015.1081248
Boltanski, L. &amp; Chiapello, E. (2007). The New Spi‑rit of Capitalism. London: Verso.
Cardoso, A. C., Tsiamis, K., Gervasini, E. et al. (2017). Citizen Science and Open Data: a model for Invasive Alien Species in Europe. Joint Research Centre (JRC) and the European Cooperation in Science and Technology (COST Association), Workshop Report. Brussels, BE. https://doi.org/10.3897/rio.3.e14811
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018182
Callon, M., Burchell, G., Lascoumes, P. &amp; Barthe, Y.  (2011). Acting in an Uncertain World: An Essay on Technical Democracy. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.
Cavoukian, A., Taylor, S. &amp; Abrams, M. E. (2010). Privacy by Design: Essential for Organizational Accountability and Strong Business Practices. Iden‑tity in the Information Society, 3(2), 405–413. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12394‑010‑0053‑z
DataShift (n.d.). Global Goals for Local Impact: Using Citizen‑Generated Data to Help Achieve Gen‑der Equality. http://civicus.org/thedatashift/wp‑content/uploads/ 2017/01/LanetUmojaProcessandApproach.pdf (accessed 22 February 2018)
European Commission (2013). Environmental Citizen Science. Science for Environment Policy Indepth Report N° 9. Bristol: University of the West of England, Science Communication Unit.http://ec.europa.eu/environment/integration/research/newsalert/pdf/IR9_en.pdf (accessed 22 February 2018)
Fleurbaey, M. (2009). Beyond GDP: The Quest for a Measure of Social Welfare. Journal of Economic literature, 47(4), 1029–1075. https://doi.org/10.1257/jel.47.4.1029
Gabrys, J., Pritchard, H. &amp; Barratt, B. (2016). Just Good Enough Data: Figuring Data Citizenships Through Air Pollution Sensing and Data Stories. Big Data &amp; Society, 3(2), 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951716679677
Gabrys, J. &amp; Pritchard, H. (2015). Just Good Enough Data and Environmental Sensing: Moving Beyond Regulatory Benchmarks toward Citizen Action. In Infrastructures and Platforms for Envi‑ronmental Crowd Sensing and Big Data. Barcelona: European Citizen Science Association.https://ecsa.citizen‑science.net/sites/default/files/envip‑2015‑draft‑binder.pdf (accessed 22 February 2018)
Goodchild, M. F. (2007). Citizens as Sensors: The World of Volunteered Geography. GeoJournal, 69(4), 211–221.https://doi.org/10.1007/s10708‑007‑9111‑y
Graham, S. (2005). Software‑Sorted Geographies. Progress in Human Geography, 29(5), 562–580. https://doi.org/10.1191/0309132505ph568oa
Grommé, F., Ustek‑Spilda, F., Ruppert, E. &amp; Cakici, B. (2017). Citizen Data and Official Sta‑tistics: Background Document to a Collaborative Workshop. ARITHMUS Working Paper N° 2.http://arithmus.eu/wp‑content/uploads/2015/02/ARITHMUS‑collaborative‑workshop‑wp_final‑ver‑sion‑060717‑1.pdf
Grommé, F. (2015). Governance by Pilot Projects: Experimenting with Surveillance in Dutch Crime Control (Doctoral thesis). Amsterdam: University of Amsterdam.http://hdl.handle.net/11245/1.486712 (accessed  6 February 2019)
Guillemin, M. &amp; Gillam, L. (2004). Ethics, Reflexivity, and “Ethically Important Moments” in Research. Qualitative Inquiry, 10(2), 261–280. https://doi.org/10.1177/1077800403262360
Henriquez, L. (2016). Amsterdam Smart Citizens Lab: Towards Community Driven Data Collection. Amsterdam: De Waag Society and AMS Institute. https://waag.org/sites/waag/files/media/publicaties/ amsterdam‑smart‑citizen‑lab‑publicatie.pdf (accessed  2 April 2017)
Hussmanns, R. (2004). Measuring the Informal Economy: From Employment in the Informal Sector to Informal Employment. Working Paper N° 53. http://www.ilo.org/wcmsp5/groups/public/‑‑‑dgreports/‑‑‑integration/documents/publication/wcms_079142.pdf (accessed 30 April 2018)
Isin, E. &amp; Ruppert, E. (2015). Being Digital Citizens. London: Rowman &amp; Littlefield International.
Isin, E. &amp; Saward, M. (2013). Enacting European Citizenship. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.
Jasanoff, S. (2003). Technologies of Humility: Citizen Participation in Governing Science. Minerva, 41(3), 223–244. https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1025557512320
Jasanoff, S. &amp; Simmet, H. R. (2017). No Funeral Bells: Public Reason in a “post‑Truth” Age. Social Studies of Science, 47(5), 751–770. https://doi.org/10.1177/0306312717731936
Jungnickel, K. (2017). Making Things to Make Sense of Things: DIY as Research Subject and Practice. In: Sayers, J. (Ed.), The Routledge Companion to Media Studies and Digital Humanities, pp. 492–502. Oxon: Routledge.
Kitchin, R. (2014). The Real‑Time City? Big Data and Smart Urbanism. GeoJournal, 79(1), 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10708‑013‑9516‑8
Kullenberg, C. &amp; Kasperowski, D. (2016). What Is Citizen Science? – A Scientometric Meta‑Analysis. PLOS ONE, 11(1), e0147152. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0147152 (accessed 2 April 2017)
ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018 183
Citizen Data and Trust in Official Statistics
Latour, B. (2004). Why Has Critique Run Out of Steam? From Matters of Fact to Matters of Concern. Critical Inquiry, 30(2), 225–248. https://doi.org/10.1086/421123
Latour, B. (2006). Which Protocol for the New  Collective Experiments? Boletín CF+S, (32/33). http://habitat.aq.upm.es/boletin/n32/ablat.en.html (accessed 2 April 2017)
Marres, N. (2012). Material Participation: Tech‑nology, the Environment and Everyday Publics. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan.
Montjoye, Y.‑A. (de), Shmueli, E., Wang, S. S. &amp; Pentland, A. S. (2014). OpenPDS: Protecting the Privacy of Metadata through SafeAnswers. PLOS ONE, 9(7). https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0098790
Muniesa, F. &amp; Linhardt, D. (2011). Trials of Expli‑citness in the Implementation of Public Management reform. Critical Perspectives on Accounting, 22(6), 550–566. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cpa.2011.06.003
Nissenbaum, H. (2004). Privacy as Contextual Inte‑grity. Washington Law Review, 79(1), 119–158. https://nyuscholars.nyu.edu/en/publications/privacy‑as‑contextual‑integrity (accessed 2 April 2017)
Nissenbaum, H. (2009). Privacy in Context: Tech‑nology, Policy, and the Integrity of Social Life. Stan‑ford: Stanford University Press.
Paul, K. T. (2018). Collective Organization of Dis‑course Expertise Using Information Technology – CODE IT! Information Technology, 60(1), 21–27. https://doi.org/10.1515/itit‑2017‑0022
Piovesan, F. (2017). Statistical Perspectives on Citizen‑Generated Data. [Online]. h t tp: / /c ivicus .org/ thedatashif t /wp‑content /uploads/2015/07/statistical‑perspectives‑on‑cgd_web_single‑page.pdf (accessed 22 February 2018)
Puig de la Bellacasa, M. (2012). “Nothing Comes Without Its World”: Thinking with Care. The Socio‑logical Review, 60(2), 197–216. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467‑954X.2012.02070.x
Rabinow, P. &amp; Bennett, G. (2012). Designing Human Practices: An Experiment with Synthetic Biology. Chicago: University of Chicago Press.
Ruppert, E. (2018). Sociotechnical Imaginaries of Different Data Futures: An Experiment in Citizen 
Data. 3e Van Doornlezing. Rotterdam, NL: Erasmus School of Behavioural and Social Sciences. https://www.eur.nl/sites/corporate/files/2018‑06/ 3e%20van%20doornlezing%20evelyn%20ruppert.pdf (accessed 21 Jan 2019)
Ruppert, E., Law, J. &amp; Savage, M. (2013). Reas‑sembling Social Science Methods: The Challenge of Digital Devices. Theory, Culture &amp; Society, Special Issue on “The Social Life of Methods”, 30(4), 22–46. https://doi.org/10.1177/0263276413484941
Ruppert, E., Harvey, P., Lury, C., Mackenzie, A.,  McNally, R., Baker, S. A., Kallianos, Y. &amp; Lewis, C. (2015). A Social Framework for Big Data. Project Report. CRESC, The University of Manchester and The Open University. http://research.gold.ac.uk/13483/ (accessed 2 April 2017)
Simon, H. (1947). Administrative Behavior: A Study of Decision‑Making Processes in Administrative Organization. New York: Macmillan.
Socientize Consortium (2014). Green Paper on Citizen Science. Citizen Science for Europe: Towards a Better Society of Empowered Citizens and Enhanced Research. European Commission Digital Science Unit. https://ec.europa.eu/digital‑single‑market/en/news/ green‑paper‑citizen‑science‑europe‑towards‑society‑ empowered‑citizens‑and‑enhanced‑research (accessed 22 February 2018)
Statistics Canada (2016). Open Building Data: An Exploratory Initiative. http://www.statcan.gc.ca/eng/crowdsourcing (accessed 18 February 2018)
Stengers, I. (2010). Cosmopolitics. Vol. 1–2.  Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.
Stiglitz, J. E., Sen, A. &amp; Fitoussi, J.‑P. (2009). Report by the Commission on the Measurement of Economic Performance and Social Progress. Paris: CMESP. http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/documents/118025/ 118123/Fitoussi+Commission+report (accessed 30 April 2018)
Struijs, P., Braaksma, B. &amp; Daas, P. J. H. (2014). Official statistics and Big Data. Big Data &amp; Society, 1(1), 1–6.https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951714538417
UNECE (2014). The Role of Big Data in the Moder‑nisation of Statistical Production Project. Report of the Big Data Privacy Task Team.http://bit.ly/2eTHDOe (accessed 2 April 2017)
 ECONOMIE ET STATISTIQUE / ECONOMICS AND STATISTICS N° 505-506, 2018184
United Nations (2014). “Fundamental Principles of Official Statistics”. Resolution adopted by the Gene‑ral Assembly on 29 January 2014. A /RES/68/261. http://unstats.un.org/unsd/dnss/gp/FP‑New‑E.pdf (accessed 21 Jan 2019)
United Nations (2016). Make Sustainable Develop‑ment Goals Relevant to Citizens. New York: Econo‑mic and Social Council. https://www.un.org/press/en/2016/ecosoc6782.doc.htm (accessed 2 April 2017)
Waterton, C. &amp; Tsouvalis, J. (2015). On the Politi‑cal Nature of Cyanobacteria: Intra‑Active Collective 
Politics in Loweswater, the English Lake District. Environment and Planning D: Society and Space, 33(3), 477–493. https://doi.org/10.1177/0263775815594305
Zwitter, A. (2014). Big Data Ethics. Big Data &amp; Society. 1(2) 1–6.https://doi.org/10.1177/2053951714559253
Zyskind, G., Nathan, O., &amp; Pentland, A. (2015). Decentralizing Privacy: Using Blockchain to Pro‑tect Personal Data. 2015 IEEE Security and Privacy Workshops, pp. 180–184.https://doi.org/10.1109/SPW.2015.27
	Informations
	Informations sur les auteurs
	Evelyn Ruppert
	Francisca Grommé
	Funda Ustek-Spilda
	Baki Cakici
	Pagination
	171
	172
	173
	174
	175
	176
	177
	178
	179
	180
	181
	182
	183
	184
	Plan
	Box – The research project
	Experimentalism
	Citizen Science
	Smart Statistics
	Privacy‑by‑Design
</TextWithNodes>
<!-- The default annotation set -->

<AnnotationSet>
</AnnotationSet>

<!-- Named annotation set -->
<AnnotationSet>
<Annotation Id="384" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="41040" EndNode="41097">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="385" Type="privacy-by-design" StartNode="41079" EndNode="41096">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="386" Type="scientific principles" StartNode="42068" EndNode="42687">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="387" Type="privacy-by-design" StartNode="43025" EndNode="43301">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="388" Type="privacy-by-design" StartNode="43968" EndNode="44183">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="390" Type="contextual integrity" StartNode="44915" EndNode="45357">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="391" Type="discrimination" StartNode="45485" EndNode="45974">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="392" Type="policy solution" StartNode="46830" EndNode="47076">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="393" Type="privacy-by-design" StartNode="48213" EndNode="48382">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="394" Type="privacy-by-design" StartNode="48784" EndNode="49039">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="395" Type="privacy-by-design" StartNode="49061" EndNode="49082">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="396" Type="future" StartNode="49819" EndNode="50101">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="397" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="50670" EndNode="51227">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="398" Type="gatekeeping" StartNode="51228" EndNode="51561">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="400" Type="citizen science model" StartNode="51562" EndNode="51935">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="401" Type="application?" StartNode="51562" EndNode="51936">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="402" Type="co-production" StartNode="53366" EndNode="53572">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="403" Type="new discourses (not new knowledge)" StartNode="54771" EndNode="54890">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="405" Type="new discourses (not new knowledge)" StartNode="55461" EndNode="55739">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="407" Type="application?" StartNode="55739" EndNode="55931">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="300" Type="title" StartNode="0" EndNode="45">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="301" Type="citizen trust" StartNode="339" EndNode="566">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="302" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="924" EndNode="1157">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="303" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="353" EndNode="438">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="304" Type="citizen trust" StartNode="1190" EndNode="1384">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="305" Type="year" StartNode="1608" EndNode="1612">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="307" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="5314" EndNode="5411">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="308" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="5698" EndNode="6123">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="309" Type="solutions" StartNode="5639" EndNode="6124">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="310" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="6416" EndNode="6744">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="311" Type="history of statistics" StartNode="7093" EndNode="7375">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="312" Type="solutions" StartNode="7376" EndNode="7633">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="313" Type="private corporations" StartNode="7814" EndNode="8032">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="314" Type="Big Data" StartNode="7814" EndNode="7822">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="315" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="8481" EndNode="8637">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="317" Type="goals" StartNode="8756" EndNode="9116">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="318" Type="agency" StartNode="8844" EndNode="9011">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="319" Type="agency" StartNode="9397" EndNode="9482">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="320" Type="method" StartNode="9117" EndNode="9365">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="321" Type="goals" StartNode="9486" EndNode="9566">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="322" Type="application?" StartNode="9486" EndNode="9565">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="323" Type="agency" StartNode="9566" EndNode="9918">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="324" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="10330" EndNode="10799">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="325" Type="subjective statistics" StartNode="11000" EndNode="11104">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="326" Type="subjective statistics" StartNode="11144" EndNode="11386">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="327" Type="democratic approach" StartNode="11152" EndNode="11291">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="328" Type="co-production" StartNode="11449" EndNode="11563">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="329" Type="co-production" StartNode="9759" EndNode="9918">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="330" Type="method" StartNode="11587" EndNode="11931">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="331" Type="method" StartNode="12594" EndNode="12760">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="332" Type="statistics reference" StartNode="13122" EndNode="13516">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="333" Type="alternative" StartNode="13517" EndNode="13778">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="334" Type="statistics reference" StartNode="13954" EndNode="14030">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="335" Type="alternative" StartNode="13953" EndNode="14030">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="337" Type="method" StartNode="14100" EndNode="14425">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="338" Type="method" StartNode="15702" EndNode="15961">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="339" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="16829" EndNode="17031">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="340" Type="method" StartNode="17192" EndNode="17418">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="342" Type="embraced experimentation" StartNode="17701" EndNode="17926">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="343" Type="embraced experimentation" StartNode="18133" EndNode="18233">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="344" Type="solutions" StartNode="18690" EndNode="19119">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="345" Type="solutions" StartNode="19532" EndNode="19716">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="346" Type="group making" StartNode="19900" EndNode="20005">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="347" Type="method" StartNode="20180" EndNode="20492">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="349" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="21214" EndNode="21486">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="351" Type="reference" StartNode="21310" EndNode="21485">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="353" Type="knowledge production" StartNode="21801" EndNode="21979">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="355" Type="method" StartNode="22235" EndNode="22669">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="357" Type="citizen trust" StartNode="23264" EndNode="23400">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="358" Type="citizen science model" StartNode="24036" EndNode="24258">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="359" Type="citizen science model" StartNode="24384" EndNode="24605">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="360" Type="citizen science model" StartNode="24607" EndNode="24734">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="361" Type="history of citizen science" StartNode="24934" EndNode="25130">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="362" Type="citizen science model" StartNode="25131" EndNode="25584">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="364" Type="citizen science platform" StartNode="26535" EndNode="26590">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="365" Type="citizen science platform" StartNode="26235" EndNode="26304">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="367" Type="benefits" StartNode="27052" EndNode="27232">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="368" Type="new discourses (not new knowledge)" StartNode="27789" EndNode="27941">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="369" Type="citizen science model" StartNode="28299" EndNode="28470">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="370" Type="scientific principles" StartNode="28961" EndNode="29073">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="371" Type="application?" StartNode="29428" EndNode="29566">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="372" Type="recording" StartNode="30044" EndNode="30392">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="373" Type="citizen science platform" StartNode="30633" EndNode="30723">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="374" Type="citizen science platform" StartNode="30874" EndNode="31161">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="375" Type="nationalistic principles" StartNode="32220" EndNode="32487">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="377" Type="political site of contention" StartNode="32488" EndNode="32811">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="378" Type="citizen trust" StartNode="33191" EndNode="33412">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="379" Type="benefits" StartNode="33840" EndNode="34067">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="380" Type="future" StartNode="35978" EndNode="36670">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="381" Type="citizen definition" StartNode="36820" EndNode="37099">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="382" Type="co-production" StartNode="40129" EndNode="40534">
</Annotation>
<Annotation Id="383" Type="co-production" StartNode="40540" EndNode="40700">
</Annotation>
</AnnotationSet>

</GateDocument>
